Downloaded From www.AllSubs.org
The story so far...
In 1975, Ed Roberts invented the Altair
personal computer.
It was a pain to use until 19 year-old
pre-billionaire Bill Gates
wrote the first personal computer language.
Still, the public didn't care.
Then two young hackers,
Steve Jobs and Steve Wozniak,
built the Apple computer
to impress their friends.
We were all impressed and Apple was
a stunning success.
By 1980, the PC market was worth
a billion dollars.
Now, view on...
We are nerds.
Most of the people in the industry were young
because the guys who had any real experience
were too smart
to get involved in all these crazy little
machines.
It really wasn't that we were going to build
billion dollar businesses.
We were having a good time.
I thought this was the most fun you
could possibly have
with your clothes on.
When the personal computer was invented
more than twenty years ago
it was just that - an invention
it wasn't a business.
These were hobbyists who built these machines
and wrote this software to have fun
but that has really changed
and now this is a business,
this is a big business.
How the personal computer industry grew
from zero to 100 million units is
an amazing story.
And it wasn't just those early funky companies
of nerds and hackers,
like Apple, that made it happen.
Most of these transformation from hobby
to big business
can be linked to three letters: IBM.
IBM was, and is, an American
business phenomenon.
Over 60 years, Tom Watson and his son,
Tom Jr., built
what their workers called Big Blue into the top
computer company in the world.
But IBM made mainframe computers for
large companies,
not personal computers,
at least not yet.
For the PC to be taken seriously by big business,
the nerds of Silicon Valley had to meet
the suits of corporate America.
IBM never fired anyone, requiring only
the undying loyalty to the company and a strict
dress code.
IBM hired conservative hard-workers
straight from school.
Few IBM'ers were at the summer of love.
Their turn-ons were giant mainframes and
corporate responsibility.
They worked nine to five and on Saturdays
washed the car.
This is intergalactic HQ for IBM,
the largest computer company in the world...
but in many ways IBM is really more a country
than it is a company.
It has hundreds of thousands of citizens,
it has a bureaucracy,
it has an entire culture - everything in fact
but an army.
OK Sam we're ready to visit IBM country,
obviously we're dressed for the part.
Now when you were in sales training in 1959
for IBM did you sing company songs?
- Absolutely.
Well just to get us in the mood
let's sing one right here.
- You're kidding.
I have the IBM - the songs of the IBM
and we're going to try for number 74,
our IBM salesmen sung to the
tune of Jingle Bells.
(Bob & Sam singing)
'IBM, happy men, smiling all the way...
oh what fun it is to sell...
our pruducts night and day....
IBM Watson men, partners of TJ...
In his service to mankind,
that's why we are so gay.'
- Now gay didn't mean what it means today
then remember that OK?
Right ok let's go.
- I guess that was OK.
Perfect.
When I started at IBM there was a dress code,
that was an informal oral code of white shirts.
You couldn't wear anything but a white shirt,
generally with a starched collar.
I remember attending my first class, and a
gentleman said to me
as we were entering the building,
"are you an IBMer?", and I said yes.
He had a three piece suit on, vests were of
the vogue,
and he said:
"could you just lift your pants leg please?"
I said what, and before I knew it he had lifted
my pants leg
and he said "you're not wearing any garters!"
I said what?!
He said "your socks, they're not pulled
tight to the top",
"you need garters." And sure enough I had
to go get garters.
IBM is like Switzerland
conservative, a little dull, yet prosperous.
It has committees to verify each decision.
The safety net is so big that it is hard
to make a bad decision
or any decision at all.
Rich Seidner, computer programmer and
wannabe Paul Simon,
spent twenty-five years marching in lockstep
at IBM.
He feels better now.
I mean it's like... getting four hundred
thousand people
to agree what they want to have for lunch.
You know... I mean it's how can I...
it's gonna be lowest common...
you know...
it's going to be, you know...
hot dogs and beans!
So ahm so what you gonna do?
So IBM had created this process and
it absolutely
made sure that quality would be preserved
throughout the process,
that you actually were doing what you set
out to do
and what you thought the customer wanted.
At one point somebody kind of looked at the
process to see well, you know,
what's it doing and what's the overhead
built into it,
what they found is that it would take at least
nine months
to ship an empty box.
By the late seventies, even IBM
had begun to notice
the explosive growth of personal computer
companies like Apple.
(commercial) the Apple 2, small inexpensive
and simple to use...
What's more, it was a computer business
they didn't control.
In 1980, IBM decided they wanted a piece
of this action.
There were suddenly tens of thousands of
people buying
machines of that class and they loved them.
They were very happy with them and they
were showing up
in the engineering departments of our clients
as machines that were brought in
because you can't do the job on your
mainframe kind of thing.
(commercial) JB wanted to know why I'm doing
better than all the other managers...
it's no secret...I have an Apple,
sure there's a big computer three flights down
but it won't test my options,
do my charts or edit my reports like my Apple.
The people who had gotten it were
religious fanatics about them.
So the concern was we were losing the hearts
and minds and give me a machine
to win back the hearts and minds.
In business, as in comedy, timing is everything,
and time looked like it might be running out
for an IBM PC.
I'm visiting an IBMer who took up the challenge.
In August 1979, as IBM's top management
met to discuss their PC crisis,
Bill Lowe ran a small lab in Boca Raton Florida.
- Hello Bob nice to see you.
Nice to see you again. I tried to match
the IBM dress code how did I do?
- That's terrific, that's terrific.
He knew the company was in a quandary.
Wait another year and the PC industry would be
too big even for IBM to take on.
Chairman Frank Carey turned to the
department heads and said:
"HELP!!!"
He kind of said well, what should we do,
and I said well,
we think we know what we would like to do if
we were going to proceed with our own product
and he said no, he said at IBM it would take
four years and three hundred people
to do anything, I mean it's just a fact of life.
And I said no sir, we can provide with product
in a year.
And he abruptly ended the meeting,
he said you're on Lowe,
come back in two weeks and tell me
what you need.
An IBM product in a year! Ridiculous!
Down in the basement Bill still has the plan.
To save time, instead of building a computer
from scratch,
they would buy components off the shelf
and assemble them
what in IBM speak was called 'open
architecture.'
IBM never did this.
Two weeks later Bill proposed his heresy
to the Chairman.
- And frankly this is it.
- The key decisions were to go with
an open architecture,
- non IBM technology, non IBM software,
non IBM sales and non IBM service.
- And we probably spent a full half of the
presentation
- carrying the corporate management committee
into this concept.
- Because this was a new concept for IBM
at that point.
Was it a hard sell?
- Mr. Carey bought it. And as result of him
buying it, we got through it.
With the backing of the chairman,
Bill and his team
then set out to break all the IBM rules and
go for a record.
- We'll put it in the IBM section.
Once IBM decided to do a personal computer
and to do it in a year, they couldn't really
design anything,
they just had to slap it together, so that's
what we'll do.
You have a central processing unit and eh...
let's see...
you need a monitor or display and...
a keyboard.
OK: a PC, except it's not, there's something
missing.
Time for the Cringely crash course in
elementary computing.
A PC is a boxful of electronic switches,
a piece of hardware.
It's useless until you tell it what to do.
It requires a program of instructions...
that's software.
Every PC requires at least two essential bits of
software in order to work at all.
First it requires a computer language.
That's what you type in to give instructions
to the computer.
To tell it what to do.
Remember it was a computer language
called BASIC
that Paul Allen and Bill Gates adapted to the
Altair...the first PC.
The other bit of software that's required is called
an operating system
and that's the internal traffic cop that tells
the computer itself
how the keyboard is connected to the screen
or how to store files on a floppy disk
instead of just losing them when you turn off the
PC at the end of the day.
Operating systems tend to have boring
unfriendly names
like UNIX and CPM and MS-DOS but, though
they may be boring,
it's an operating system that made Bill Gates
the richest man in the world.
And the story of how that came about is, well,
pretty interesting.
So the contest begins.
Who would IBM buy their software from?
Let's meet the two contenders: the late
Gary Kildall, then aged 39,
a computer Ph.D., and a 24 year old Harvard
drop-out - Bill Gates.
By the time IBM came calling in 1980,
Bill Gates and his small company Microsoft
was the biggest supplier
of computer languages in the fledgling
PC industry.
(Commercial)
- Many different computer manufacturers,
- are making the CPM Operating System standard
on most models.
For their operating system, though,
the logical guy for the IBMers to see was
Gary Kildall.
He ran a company modestly called
'Interglactic Digital Research.'
Gary had invented the PC's first operating system
called CP/M.
He had already sold 600,000 of them, so he was
the big cheese of operating systems.
- In the early 70s I had a need for an
operating system myself
- and eh it was a very natural thing to write
- and it turns out other people had a need for
an operating system like that and so
- eh it was a very natural thing I wrote it for my own
use and then started selling it.
In Gary's mind it was the dominant thing and
it would always be the dominant
'cos, you know,  Bill did languages and Gary did
operating systems
and he really honestly believed that would
never change.
But what would change the balance of power
in this young industry
was the characters of the two protagonists.
- So I knew Gary back when he was an assistant
professor
- at Monterrey Post Grad School and I was simply
a grad student.
- And went down, sat in his hot tub, smoked dope
with him and thoroughly enjoyed it all,
- and commiserated and talked nerd stuff.
- He liked playing with gadgets, just like Woz did
and does,
- just like I did and do.
He wasn't really interested in how you drive
the business,
he worked on projects, things that interested him.
He didn't go rushing off to the patent office and
patent CPM and patent every line of code he could,
he didn't try to just squeeze the last dollar out of it.
- Gary was not a fighter, Gary avoided conflict,
Gary hated conflict.
- Bill I don't think anyone could say
backed away from conflict.
Nobody said future billionaires have to be
nice guys.
Here, at the Microsoft Museum, is a shrine to
Bill's legacy.
Bill Gates hardly fought his way up from the gutter.
Raised in a prosperous Seattle household, his
mother a homemaker who did charity work,
his father was a successful lawyer.
But beneath the affluence and comfort of
a perfect American family,
a competitive spirit ran deep.
I ended up spending Memorial Day Weekend
with him
out at his grandmother's house on Hood Canal.
She turned everything in to a game.
It was a very very very competitive environment,
and if you spent the weekend there,
you were part of the competition,
and it didn't matter whether it was hearts or
pickleball or swimming to the dock.
And you know and there was always a reward
for winning
and there was always a penalty for losing.
One time, it was funny, I went to
Bill's house and he really wanted to show me his
jigsaw puzzle that he was working on,
and he really wanted to talk about how he did
this jigsaw puzzle in like four minutes,
and like on the box it said, if you're a genius you
will do the jigsaw puzzle in like seven.
And he was into it. He was like "I can do it". And I
said don't, you know, I believe you.
You don't need to break it up and do it for me.
You know.
Bill Gates can be so focused
that the small things in life get overlooked.
If he was busy he didn't bathe, he didn't
change clothes.
We were in New York and the demo that we
had crashed
the evening before the announcement, and Bill
worked all night with some other engineers to fix it.
Well it didn't occur to him to take ten minutes
for a shower after that,
it just didn't occur to him that that was important,
and he badly needed a shower that day.
The scene is set:
in California laid back Gary Kildall already making
the best selling PC operating system: CPM.
In Seattle Bill Gates maker of BASIC the best selling
PC language
but always prepared to seize an opportunity.
So IBM had to choose one of these guys
to write the operating system for its new
personal computer.
One would hit the jackpot the other
would be forgotten,
a footnote in the history of the personal computer,
and it all starts with a telephone call to an
eighth floor office
in that building the headquarters of Microsoft
in 1980.
At about noon I guess I called Bill Gates on Monday
and said I would like to come out and talk with him
about his products.
Bill said well, how's next week, and they said we're
on an airplane,
we're leaving in an hour, we'd like to be there
tomorrow. Well, hallelujah. Right oh.
Steve Ballmer was a Harvard roommate of Gates.
He'd just joined Microsoft and would end up
its third billionaire.
Back then he was the only guy in the company
with business training.
Both Ballmer and Gates instantly saw the
importance of the IBM visit.
And Bill said Steve, you'd better come to
the meeting,
you're the only other guy here who can wear a suit.
A lot of these computer fairs discussions would get
around to, you know, I...
we'll put on suits and we'll go to this meeting.
We got there at roughly two o'clock
and we were waiting in the front,
and this young fella came out to take us back to
Mr. Gates office.
I thought he was the office boy, and of course
it was Bill.
He was quite decisive, we popped out the
non-disclosure agreement
the letter that said he wouldn't tell anybody
we were there
and that we wouldn't hear any secrets and so forth.
He signed it immediately.
IBM didn't make it easy. You had to sign all these
funny agreements that sort of said
I...IBM could do whatever they wanted,
whenever they wanted
and use your secrets however they - they felt.
But so it took a little bit of faith.
Jack Sams was looking for a package from Microsoft
containing both the BASIC computer language
and an Operating System.
But IBM hadn't done their homework.
They thought we had an operating system.
Because we had this Soft Card product that
had CPM on it, they thought
we could licence them CPM for this new
personal computer
they told us they wanted to do, and we said well,
no, we're not in that business.
When we discovered we didn't have -
he didn't have the rights to do that
and that it was not...he said but I think it's ready,
I think that Gary's got it ready to go.
So I said well, there's no time like the present,
call up Gary.
And so Bill right there with them in the room,
called Gary Kildall at Digital Research
and said Gary, I'm sending some guys down.
They're going to be on the phone. Treat them right,
they're important guys.
The men from IBM came to this Victorian House
in Pacific Grove California,
headquarters of Digital Research, headed by
Gary and Dorothy Kildall.
Just imagine what its like having IBM come to visit,
its like having the Queen drop by for tea,
its like having the Pope come by looking for advice,
its like a visit from God himself.
And what did Gary and Dorothy do?
They sent them away.
Gary had some other plans and so he said well,
Dorothy will see you. So we went down the three
of us...
IBM showed up with an IBM non-disclosure and
Dorothy made what I...
a decision which I think it's easy in retrospect to say
was dumb.
We popped out our letter that said please don't tell
anybody we're here,
and we don't want to hear anything confidential.
And she read it and said and "I can't sign this".
She did what her job was, she got the lawyer
to look at the nondisclosure.
The lawyer, Gerry Davis who's still in Monterey
threw up on this non-disclosure.
It was uncomfortable for IBM, they weren't used
to waiting.
And it was unfortunate situation - here you are in a
tiny Victorian House,
its overrun with people, chaotic.
So we spent the whole day in Pacific Grove
debating with them
and with our attorneys and her attorneys and
everybody else about whether or not
she could even talk to us about talking to us,
and we left.
This is the moment Digital Research dropped
the ball.
IBM, distinctly unimpressed with their reception,
went back to Microsoft.
Bill Gates isn't the man to give a rival
a second chance.
He saw the opportunity of a lifetime.
Digital research didn't seize that, and we knew
it was essential,
if somebody didn't do it, the project was going
to fall apart.
We just got carried away and said look, we can't
afford to lose the language business.
That was the initial thought - we can't afford to have
IBM not go forward.
This is the most exciting thing that's going to
happen in PCs.
And we were already out on a limb,
because we had licensed them not only Basic,
but Fortran, Cobol Assembler er,
Typing Tutor and Venture.
And basically every - every product
the company had
we had committed to do for IBM in a very short
time frame.
But there was a problem.
IBM needed an operating system fast and
Microsoft didn't have one.
What they had was a stroke of luck - the ingredient
everyone needs to be a billionaire.
Unbelievably, the solution was just across town.
Paul Allen, Gates's programming partner
since high school,
had found another operating system.
There's a local company here in CL called
CL Computer Products
by a guy named Tim Patterson and he had done
an operating system
a very rudimentary operating system that was
kind of like CPM.
And we just told IBM look, we'll go and get this
operating system from this small local company,
we'll take care of it, we'll fix it up, and you can still
do a PC.
Tim Patterson's operating system, which saved
the deal with IBM,
was, well, adapted from Gary Kildall's CPM.
So I took a CPM manual that I'd gotten from the
Retail Computer Store five dollars
in 1976 or something, and used that as the basis for
what would be the application program interface,
the API for my operating system.
And so using these ideas that came from different
places I started in April
and it was about half time for four months before I
had my first working version.
This is it, the operating system Tim Patterson wrote.
He called in QDOS the quick and dirty
operating system.
Microsoft and IBM called it PC DOS 1.0 and under
any name it looks an awful lot like CPM.
On this computer here I have running a PC DOS and
CPM 86
and frankly itÍs very hard to tell the difference
between the two.
The command structures are the same,
so are the directories,
in fact the only obvious external difference is the
floppy dirive is labelled A in PC DOS
and and C in CPM.
Some difference and yet one generated billions in
revenue and the other disappeared.
As usual in the PC business the prize didn't go to
the inventor
but to the exploiter of the invention.
In this case that wasn't Gary Kildall, it wasn't even
Tim Paterson.
There was still one problem.
Tim Patterson worked for Seattle Computer
Products, or SCP.
They still owned the rights to QDOS,
rights that Microsoft had to have.
But then we went back and said to them look,
you know,
we want to buy this thing, and SCP was like most
little companies, you know.
They always needed cash and so that was when
they went in to the negotiation.
- And so ended up working out a deal to buy the
operating system from him
- for whatever usage we wanted for
fifty thousand dollars.
Hey, let's pause there.
To savour an historic moment.
- for whatever usage we wanted for
fifty thousand dollars.
It had to be the deal of the century if not
the millenium,
it was certainly the deal that made Bill Gates
and Paul Allen multi billionaires
and allowed Paul Allen to buy toys like these, his own
NBA basketball team and arena.
Microsoft bought outright for fifty thousand dollars
the operating system they needed
and they turned around and licensed it to the world
for up to fifty dollars per PC.
Think of it: one hundred million personal computers
running MS DOS software
funnelling billions into Microsoft - a company that
back then was
fifty kids managed by a twenty-five year old
who needed to wash his hair.
Nice work if you can get it and Microsoft got it.
There are no two places further apart in the USA
than south eastern Florida
and Washington State where Microsoft is based.
This - this is Florida,
Boca Raton and this building right here is where the
IBM PC was developed.
Here the nerds from Seattle joined forces
with the suits of corporate
and in that first honeymoon year they pulled off
a fantastic achievement.
- After we got a package in the mail from the people
down in Florida...
As August 1981 approached, the deadline for the
launch of the IBM Acorn,
the PC industry held its breath.
- Supposedly, maybe at this very moment eh,
- IBM is announcing the personal computer.
We don't know that yet.
In companies across America, software writers
like Dan Bricklin,
the creator of the first spreadsheet,
waited with their staff for the news of
the announcement.
This is a moment of PC history. IBM secrecy had
codenamed the PC 'The Floridian Project.'
Everyone in the PC business knew IBM would
change their world forever.
They also knew that if their software was
on the IBM PC,
they would make fortunes.
-...the attached information is not to be disclosed
prior to any public announcement.
- It's on the ticker
- It's on the ticker OK so now you can tell people.
What we're watching, are the first few seconds
of a $100 billion industry.
(promos) After years of thinking big today IBM
came up with something small...
...Big Blue is looking for a slice of Apple's
market share...
...Bits and Bytes mean nothing try this one...
...Now they're going to sell $1,000 computers
to millions of customers...
...I have seen the future said one analyst
and it computes.
Nobody was ever fired for buying IBM.
Now companies could put PCs with the name they
trusted on desks from Wisconsin to Wall Street.
What IBM said was it's okay corporate America for
you to now start buying and using PCs.
And if it's okay for corporate America, it's got
to be okay for everybody.
For all the hype, the IBM PC wasn't much better
than what came before.
So while the IBM name could create
immense demand,
it took a killer application to sustain it.
The killer app for the IBM PC was yet
another spreadsheet.
Based on Visicalc, but called Lotus 1-2-3,
its creators were the first of many
to get rich on IBM's success.
Within a year Lotus was worth $150 million bucks.
Wham! Bam! Thank you IBM!
IBM had forecast sales of half a million computers
by 1984.
In those 3 years, they sold 2 million.
Euphoric I guess is the right word.
Everybody was believed that they were
not going to...
At that point two million or three million,
you know,
they were now thinking in terms of a hundred
million and
they were probably off the scale
in the other direction.
What did all this mean to Bill Gates,
whose operating system, DOS,
was at the heart of every IBM PC sold?
Initially, not much, because of the deal with IBM.
But it did give him a vital bridgehead to
other players in the PC marketplace,
which meant trouble in the long run for Big Blue.
The key to our...the structure of our deal was that
IBM had no control over...
over our licensing to other people.
In a lesson on the computer industry in
mainframes was that er, over time,
people built compatible machines or clones,
whatever term you want to use,
and so really, the primary upside on the deal
we had with IBM,
because they had a fixed fee er, we got about
$80,000
we got some other money for some special work
we did er,
but no royalty from them.
And that's the DOS and Basic as well.
And so we were hoping a lot of other people
would come along and do compatible machines.
There were other PCs that were sorta like the
IBM PC, kinda like it.
But IBM now had fifty per cent market share and
was defining what a PC meant.
What the public wanted was IBM PCs.
So to be successful other manufacturers would
have to build computers exactly like the IBM.
They wanted to copy the IBM PC, to clone it.
How could they do that legally?
Well, welcome to the world of reverse engineering.
This is what reverse engineering can get you
if you do it right.
It's the modest Aspen, Colorado ski shack of
Rod Canion,
one of the founders of Compaq, the company set
up to compete head-on with the IBM PC.
Back in 1982, Rod and three fellow engineers
from Texas Instruments
sketched out a computer design on a place mat
at the House of Pies restaurant in Houston, Texas.
They decided to manufacture and market
a portable version of the IBM PC
using the curious technique of
reverse engineering.
Reverse engineering is figuring out after something
has already been created
how it ticks, what makes it work,
usually for the purpose of creating something
that works the same way or at least does
something like the thing you're trying to
reverse engineer.
Here's how you clone a PC.
IBM had made it easy to copy.
The microprocessor was available off the shelf
from Intel
and the other parts came from many sources.
Only one part was IBM's alone, a vital chip that
connected the hardware with the software.
Called the ROM-BIOS, this was IBM's own design,
protected by copyright
and Big Blue's army of lawyers.
Compaq had to somehow copy the chip
without breaking the law.
- First you have to decide how the ROM works,
- so what we had to do was have an engineer sit
down with that code
- and through trial and error write a specification
that said
- here's how the BIOS ROM needs to work.
It couldn't be close it had to be exact
- so there was a lot of detailed testing that went on.
You test how that all-important chip behaves,
and make a list of what it has to do
now it's time to meet my lawyer, Claude.
I've examined the internals of the ROM BIOS and
written this book of specifications
now I need some help because I've done
as much as I can do,
and you need to explain what's next.
- Well, the first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to
go through the book of specifications myself,
- but the first thing I can tell you Robert is that
you're out of it now.
- You are contaminated, you are dirty.
- You've seen the product that's the original work
of authorship, you've seen the target product,
- so now from here on in we're going to be working
with people who are not dirty.
- We're going to be working with so called virgins,
- who are going to be operating in the clean room.
I certainly don't qualify there.
- I imagine you don't.
- So what we're going to do is this: we're going to
hire a group of engineers
- who have never seen the IBM ROM BIOS.
- They have never seen it, they have never operated
it, they know nothing about it.
(Claude interrogates Mark) - Have you ever before
attempted to disassemble decompile or to
- in any way shape or form reverse engineer any IBM
equipment?
Oh no.
- And have you ever tried to disassemble...
This is the Silicon Valley virginity test.
And good virgins are hard to find.
- You understand that in the event that we discover
that the information you are providing us
- is inaccurate you are subject to discipline by
the company
- and that can include but not limited to termination
immediately do you understand that?
Yes I do.
- OK
After the virgins are deemed intact,
they are forbidden contact with the outside world
while they build a new chip,
one that behaves exactly like the one in
the specifications.
In Compaq's case, it took 15 senior programmers
several months and cost $1 million
to do the reverse engineering.
In November 1982, Rod Canion unveiled the result.
- What I've brought today is a Compaq
portable computer.
When Bill Murto, another Compaq founder got
a plug on a cable TV show
their selling point was clear: 100 percent
IBM compatibility.
- ...It turns out that all major popular software runs
- on the IBM personal computer or the Compaq
portable computer.
-- That extends through all of this software for IBM?
- Eh Yes.
-- It all works on the Compaq?
The Compaq was an instant hit.
In their first year,
on the strength of being exactly like IBM but a little
cheaper, they sold 47,000 PCs.
- In our first year of sales we set an American
business record.
- I guess maybe a world business record.
Largest first year sales in history.
- It was a hundred and eleven million dollars.
So Rod Canion ends up in Aspen, famous for having
the most expensive real estate in America
and I try not to look envious while Rod tells me
which executive jet he plans to buy next.
- And finally I picked the Lear 31.
Oh really?
- Now that was a fun airplane.
Oh yeh.
Poor Big Blue! Suddenly everybody was cashing in
on IBM's success.
The most obvious winner at first was Intel,
maker of the PCs microprocessor chip.
Intel was selling chips like hotcakes to
clonemakers,
and making them smaller, quicker and cheaper.
This was unheard of!
What kind of an industry had Big Blue
gotten themselves into?
- Things get less expensive every year. People
aren't used to that in general.
- I mean, you buy a new car, you buy one now
- and four years later you go and buy one it costs
more than the one you bought before.
- Here is this magical piece of an industry,
- you go buy one later it costs less, and it does
more, what a wonderful thing!
- But it causes some funny things to occur when
you think about an industry.
- An industry where prices are coming down,
where you have to sell it and use it right now,
because if you wait later it's worthless.
Where Compaq led, others soon followed.
IBM was now facing dozens of rivals - soon to be
familiar names began to appear,
like Amstrad, AST and Dell.
It was getting spectacularly easy to build a clone.
You could get everything off the shelf, including
a guaranteed-virgin ROM BIOS chip.
Each new clonemaker, free of IBM's big overhead,
took another bite of the big blue business.
Well, they really hit with a vengeance in '85,
the prices were going down
on the competitive products had about 30%
every six months.
- Terror would be a good phrase.
Terror?
- Oh, of course. I mean we were able to sell
a lot of products
- but it was getting difficult to make money.
And where did every clone-maker buy his
operating system?
Microsoft, of course.
By the mid 80's it was boom time for Bill.
The teenage entrepreneur had predicted a PC on
every desk and in every home,
running Microsoft software, it was actually
coming true.
As Microsoft mushroomed there was no way that
Bill Gates could personally dominate
thousands of employees but that didn't stop him.
He still had a need to be both industry titan
and top programmer.
So he had to come up with a whole new corporate
culture for Microsoft.
He had to find a way to satisfy both his adolescent
need to dominate
and his adult need to inspire.
From the beginning, Microsoft recruited
straight out of college.
They chose people who had no experience of life
in other companies.
In time they'd be called Microserfs.
And so a lot of young, I say people, but mostly
it was young men,
who just were out of school saw him as this
incredible role model or leader,
almost a guru I guess.
And they could spend hours with him and he
valued their contributions
and there was just a wonderful camaraderie
that seemed to exist between all these
young men and Bill,
and this strength that he has and his will and his
desire to be the best
and to be the winner - he is just like a cult leader,
really.
As the frenzied 80's came to a close IBM reached
a watershed
they had created an open PC architecture that
anyone could copy.
This was intentional but IBM always thought their
inside track would keep them ahead.
Wrong.
IBM's glacial pace and high overhead put them at
a disadvantage to the leaner clone makers
everything was turning into a nightmare as IBM
lost its dominant market share.
So in a big gamble they staked their PC future
to a new system
a new line of computers with proprietary closed
hardware and their very own operating system.
It was war.
(Presentation)
- ...start planning for operating system 2 today...
IBM planned to steal the market from Gates with
a brand new operating system, called
- drum roll please -
OS/2.
IBM would design OS/2. Yet they asked Microsoft
to write the code.
Why would Microsoft help create what was
intended to be the instrument
of their own destruction?
Because Microsoft knew IBM was was the source
of their success
and they would tolerate almost anything
to stay close to Big Blue.
It was just part of, as we used to call it, the time
riding the bear.
You just had to try to stay on the bear's back and
the bear would twist and turn
and try to buck you and throw you, but darn,
we were going to ride the bear
because the bear was the biggest, the most
important you just had to be with the bear,
otherwise you would be under the bear in the
computer industry, and IBM was the bear,
and we were going to ride the back of the bear.
It's easy for people to forget how pervasive IBM's
influence over this industry was.
When you talked to people who've come in to the
industry recently
there's no way you can get that in to their,
in to their head,
that was the environment.
The relationship between IBM and Microsoft
was always a culture clash.
IBMers were buttoned-up organization men.
Microsoftees were obsessive hackers.
With the development of OS/2 the strains
really began to show.
In IBM there's a religion in software that says you
have to count K-LOCs,
and a K-LOC is a thousand line of code.
How big a project is it? Oh, it's sort of a 10K-LOC
project.
This is a 20K-LOCer. And this is 5OK-LOCs.
And IBM wanted to sort of make it the religion
about how we got paid.
How much money we made off OS 2, how much
they did. How many K-LOCs did you do?
and we kept trying to convince them: hey, if we
have - a developer's got a good idea
and he can get something done in 4K-LOCs
instead of 20K-LOCs,
should we make less money?
Because he's made something smaller and
faster, less KLOC.
K-LOCs, K-LOCs, that's the methodology.
Ugh anyway, that always makes my back just
crinkle up at the thought of the whole thing.
When I took over in '89 there was an enormous
amount of resources working on OS 2,
both in Microsoft and the IBM company.
Bill Gates and I met on that several times. And
we pretty quickly came to the conclusion together
that that was not going to be a success,
the way it was being managed.
It was also pretty clear that the negotiating and
the contracts
had given most of that control to Microsoft.
It was no longer just a question of styles. There
was now a clear conflict of business interest.
OS/2 was planned to undermine the
clone market,
where DOS was still Microsoft's major
money-maker.
Microsoft was DOS. But Microsoft was helping
develop the opposition?
Bad idea. To keep DOS competitive,
Gates had been pouring resources into
a new programme called Windows.
It was designed to provide a nice user-friendly
facade to boring old DOS.
Selling it was another job for shy, retiring
Steve Ballmer.
- How much do you think this advanced operating
environment is worth?
- wait just one minute before you answer
- watch as Windows integrates Lotus 1, 2, 3 with
Miami Vice. Now we can take this...
Just as Bill Gates saw OS/2 as a threat,
IBM regarded Windows
as another attempt by Microsoft to hold on to
the operating system business.
We created Windows in parallel. We kept saying to
IBM, hey, Windows is the way to go,
graphics is the way to go, and we got virtually
everyone else,
enthused about Windows. So that was a
divergence that we kept thinking
we could get IBM to - to come around on.
It was clear that IBM had a different vision of its
relationship with Microsoft
than Microsoft had of its vision with IBM.
Was that Microsoft's fault?
You know, maybe some ,but IBM's not
blameless there either.
So I don't view any of that as anything but
just poor business on IBM's part.
Bill Gates is a very disciplined guy.
He puts aside everything he wants to read,
and twice a year goes away for secluded
reading weeks.
The decisive moment in the Microsoft/IBM
relationship came during just such a retreat.
In front of a log fire Bill concluded that it was
no longer
in Microsoft's long term interests to
blindly follow IBM.
If Bill had to choose between OS2, IBM's
new operating system and Windows,
he'd choose Windows.
We said ooh, IBM's probably not going to like this.
This is going to threaten OS 2.
Now we told them about it, right away we told
them about it, but we still did it.
They didn't like it, we told em about it,
we told em about it,
we offered to licence it to em.
We always thought the best thing to do is to try
and combine
IBM promoting the software with us doing
the engineering.
And so it was only when they broke off
communication and decided to go their own way
that we thought, okay, we're on our own,
and that was definitely very, very scary.
We were in a major negotiation in early 1990,
right before the Windows launch.
We wanted to have IBM on stage with us
to launch Windows 3.0,
but they wouldn't do the kind of deal that would
allow us to profit it would allow them
essentially to take over Windows from us, and we
walked away from the deal.
Jack Sams, who started IBM's relationship with
Microsoft with that first call
to Bill Gates in 1980, could only look on as the
partnership disintegrated.
Then they at that point I think they agreed
to disagree
on the future progress of OS 2 and Windows.
And internally we were told thou shalt not ship
any more products on Windows.
And about that time I got the opportunity
to take early retirement so I did.
Bill's decison by the fireplace ended the ten year
IBM/Microsoft partnership
and turned IBM into an also-ran in the PC
business.
Did David beat Goliath?
The Boca Raton, Florida birthplace of the IBM's PC
is deserted,
a casualty of diminishing market share.
Today, IBM is again what it was before:
a profitable, dominant mainframe computer
company.
For awhile IBM dominated the PC market.
They legitimised the PC business,
created the standards most of us now use,
and introduced the PC
to the corporate world.
But in the end they lost out.
Maybe it was to a faster, more flexible
business culture.
Or maybe they just threw it away.
That's the view of a guy who's been competing
with IBM for 20 years,
Silicon Valley's most outspoken software
billionaire, Larry Ellison.
I think IBM made the single worst mistake in
the history of enterprise on earth.
- Which was?
Which was the manufacture
being the first manufacturer and distributor of
the Microsoft/Intel PC
which they mistakenly called the IBM PC.
I mean they were the first manufacturer and
distributor of that technology
I mean it's just simply astounding that they
could ah...
basically give a third of their market value
to Intel
and a third of their market value to Microsoft
by accident
I mean no-one, no-one... I mean those two
companies today are worth
close to you know approaching
a hundred billion dollars
I mean not many of us get a chance to make
a $100 billion mistake.
As fast as IBM abandons its buildings, Microsoft
builds new ones.
In 1980 IBM was 3000 times the size of Microsoft.
Though still a smaller company, today Wall Street
says Microsoft is worth more.
Both have faced anti-trust investigations about
their monopoly positions.
For years IBM defined successful American corporate
culture - as a machine of ordered bureaucracy.
Here in the corridors of Microsoft it's a different
style, it's personal.
This company - in its drive, its hunger to succeed,
is a reflection of one man, its founder, Bill Gates.
Bill wanted to win.
Incredible desire to win and to beat other people.
At Microsoft we, the whole idea was that we would
put people under, you know.
And unfortunately, ah... that's happened a lot.
Bill Gates is special. You wouldn't have had
a Microsoft
with take a random other person like Gary Kildall.
On the other hand, Bill Gates was also lucky.
But Bill Gates knows that, unlike a lot of other
people in the industry, and he's paranoid.
Every morning he gets up and he doesn't feel
secure, he feels nervous about this.
They're trying hard, they're not relaxing, and that's
why they're so successful.
And I remember, I was talking to Bill once and I
asked him what he feared,
and he said that he feared growing old because, you
know, once you're beyond thirty,
this was his belief at the time, you know once you're
beyond thirty, you know,
you don't have as many good ideas anymore.
You're not as smart anymore.
If you just slow down a little bit who knows who
it'll be,
probably some company that may not even
exist yet,
but eh someone else can come in and take the lead.
And I said well, you know, you're going to age, it's
going to happen, it's kind of inevitable,
what are you going to do about it?
And he said I'm just going to hire the smartest
people and I'm going to surround myself
with all these smart people, you know.
And I thought that was kind of interesting.
It was almost - it was like he was like oh,
I can't be immortal, but like maybe this is the
second best and I can buy that, you know.
If you miss what's happening then the same kind of
thing that happened to IBM
or many other companies could happen to
Microsoft very easily.
So no-one's got a guaranteed position in the high
technology business, and the more you think about,
you know, how could we move faster, what could
we do better,
are there good ideas out there that we should be
going beyond, it's important.
And I wouldn't trade places with anyone, but the
reason I like my job so much is
that we have to constantly stay on top of
those things.
The Windows software system that ended the alliance
between Microsoft and IBM
pushed Gates past all his rivals.
Microsoft had been working on the software for
years, but it wasn't until 1990 that they finally
came up with a version that not only worked
properly, it blew their rivals away,
and where did the idea for this software come from?
Well not from Microsoft, of course.
It came from the hippies at Apple.
Lights! Camera! Boot up! In 1984, they made a
famous TV commercial.
Apple had set out to create the first user-friendly
PC just as IBM and Microsoft
were starting to make a machine for businesses.
When the TV commercial aired, Apple launched
the Macintosh.
The computer and the commercial were aimed
directly at IBM
which the kids in Cupertino thought of as
Big Brother.
But Apple had targeted the wrong people.
It wasn't Big Brother they should have been worrying
about, it was big Bill Gates.
subtitles by fabiusX
subs@fabiushouse.com
Downloaded From www.AllSubs.org