The story so far,
In 1980, just four years after being founded
in a Californian garage,
Apple was the biggest maker of PCs in the world.
Computer giant IBM was not amused and fought back,
launching its own PC in 1981.
Though built from copy-cat technology,
IBM's PC was an enormous hit and spawned many imitators,
the PC clones.
But PCs were still a pain to use.
A revolution was needed to make them friendlier.
Now, view on.
Ladies and gentlemen welcome to the launch of Windows 95.
Yes, welcome Microsoftees nice to have you all here.
But now let's welcome the chairman of Microsoft.
Listen to this. This is a man, a man so successful
his chaffeur is Ross Perot ladies and gentlemen...
please welcome Bill Gates.
It's August 24th, 1995.
In a suburb of Seattle in the Pacific Northwest,
this is the biggest, noisiest product launch
in the history of the personal computer.
It's Windows 95 software - and Bill Gates is the star, chairman,
chief nerd and spiritual leader of Microsoft.
This is the latest step in Bill's dream to have
his software running on every PC in the world.
Bill Gates: We wanted people to be able to appreciate
how Windows 95 makes computing
faster, easier and more fun.
And for seven years it was a lonely, lonely crusade...
this moves the whole PC industry up to a whole new level...
Wait a minute all this publicity is so Bill Gates
can claim that Windows 95 is the latest
and perhaps the most significant improvement
in the PC since it was invented.
He can say that his new operating system makes PC's
nicer to look at and easier to use than ever before.
They'll no longer be just for geeks and nerds they'll be
so easy to use that even my mother will want one...
but you know what - most of the ideas in Windows 95
were invented twenty years ago.
The 20 year journey to this software celebration hasn't been easy.
It has involved huge gambles,
passionate commitment, dramatic setbacks
and required the occasional crushing of rivals and allies.
It's the triumph of Bill Gates' commercial vision.
Success in the market place doesn't have to come
from innovation, or from being the best,
if you have a ruthless ability to exploit your opportunities.
And the way Microsoft made the PC's graphical user interface
its own is a textbook example of that ability.
Time for another Cringely crash course in elementary computing.
In the early days of personal computing
the machines were pretty hard to use
in part that's because they were primitive
but it's also because computer guys
tend to like things that are pretty hard to use.
This is an IBM PC circa about 1983
and on it I have written a letter to my bank manager
asking him to back one of my get rich quick schemes
and I need to file the letter now and let me show you
how I do it - there will be a test on this.
OK the commands are - copy c, colon, backslash,
quickrich, dot, doc space a colon backslash
begging and return - well not very easy to do.
Here's a windows PC about twelve years newer
and we'll do exactly the same thing
I've written a document - quickrich, dot doc
and I put it in the begging file
and it yes I really do mean to do it and that's it.
Pictures rather than words making the PC easy and intuitive.
This is called a graphical user interface - GUI or gooey
where they come up with these names.
The battle to bring gooeys to PCs
and make them more user friendly
took ten years and is a helluva story
that is what this program is about.
It's also about how Bill Gates ended up
master of the gooey universe and a gazillionaire.
I never said it was a fairy story.
It all began in 1971 in Palo Alto,
just south of San Francisco,
when Xerox, the copier company, set up the
Palo Alto Research Center, or PARC.
The Xerox management had a sinking feeling
that if people started reading
computer screens instead of paper,
Xerox was in trouble.
Unless... they could dominate
the paperless office of the future.
You could take computer technology into the office
and make the office a much better place to work,
more productive, more enjoyable
a lot more enjoyable, ehm more interesting,
more rewarding and so we set to work on it.
Bob Taylor ran the PARC's Computer Science Lab
and one of the first things he did was to buy
bean bags for his researchers to sit on and brainstorm.
Here's a couple of the original beanbag chairs.
The role of the beanbag in computer science is ease of use.
- OK.
It was said that of the top 100 computer researchers in the world,
58 worked at PARC.
Strange, as the staff never exceeded 50.
See you didn't get your butt low enough...
But Taylor gave these nerd geniuses unlimited resources
and protected them from commercial pressures.
BOB: It's very comfortable.
BOB TAYLOR: Now let's see you get out of it.
BOB: I feel my neural capacity already increasing - Oh God...
The atmosphere was electric eh there was total intellectual freedom.
There was no conventional wisdom almost every idea
was up for challenge and got challenged regularly.
The management said go create the new world.
We don't understand it.
Here are people who have a lot of ideas
and tremendous talent, young, energetic.
People came there specifically to work
on five year programs that were their dreams.
This is a computer room in the basement of
the Xerox Pala Alto Research Centre...
about twenty five years ago they built
the max time sharing system in here
and now it's loaded with all sorts of other computers
and eh there's one that we're really interested in here
let's see... here it is... let me turn on the lights.
OK, here we have it.
This is a Xerox/Alto computer built around 1973.
Some people would argue that this is the first personal computer.
Ah it really isn't because for one thing
it wasn't ever for sale
and the parts alone cost about $10,000 but
it has all the elements of quite a modern personal computer
and without it we wouldn't have the Macintosh, we wouldn't have Windows
we wouldn't have most of the things we value in computing today
and ironically none of those things has a Xerox name on it.
Commercial:
What's the mail this morning?
This promotional film made in the mid seventies,
to flaunt XEROX PARC research,
shows just how revolutionary the Alto was.
It was friendly and intuitive.
Commercial:
This is an experimental office system. It's in use now...
It had the first GUI using a mouse to
point to information on the screen.
It was linked to other PCs, by a system called ethernet,
the first computer network.
And what you saw on the screen was precisely
what you got on your laser printer.
It was way ahead of its time.
Commercial:
Thank you Fred.
Everybody wanted to make a real difference,
we really thought that we were changing the world
and that at the end of this project or this set of projects
personal computing would burst on the scene exactly the way
we had envisioned it and take everybody by total surprise.
But the brilliant researchers at PARC could never persuade
the Xerox management that their vision was accurate.
Head Office in New York ignored the revolutionary technologies
they owned three thousand miles away.
They just didn't get it.
And none of the main body of the company
was prepared to accept the answers.
So there was a tremendous mismatch between
the management and what the researchers were doing
and these guys had never fantasised about
what the future of the office was going to be
and when it was presented to them they had no mechanisms
for turning those ideas into real live products
and that was really the frustrating part of it because
you were talking to people who didn't understand the vision
and yet the vision was getting created everyday
within the Palo Alto Research Centre
and there was no one to receive that vision.
But a few miles down the road from Palo Alto
was a man ready to share the vision.
The most dangerous man in Silicon Valley
sits in an office in this building.
People love him and hate him.
Often at the same time.
For ten years by sheer force of will he made
the personal computer industry follow his direction.
With this guy we're not talking about someone driven by the profit motive
in a desire for an opulent retirement at the age of forty,
no we're talking holy war we're talking rivers of blood
and fields of dead martyrs to the cause of greater computing.
We're talking about a guy who sees the personal computer
as his tool for changing the world.
We're talking about Steve Jobs.
Hi, I'm Steve Jobs.
When I wasn't sure what the word charisma meant,
I met Steve Jobs and then I knew.
Steve Jobs is on my eternal heroes list,
there's nothing he can ever do to get off it.
He wanted you to be great and he wanted you
to create something that was great
and he was going to make you do that.
He's also obnoxious and this comes from his high standards.
He has extremely high standards and he has no patience with people
who don't either share those standards or perform to them.
And I'm also one of these people.
I don't really care about being right
you know I just care about success.
Steve Jobs had co-founded Apple Computer in 1976.
The first popular personal computer, the Apple 2, was a hit
and made Steve Jobs one of the biggest names in a brand-new industry.
At the height of Apple's early success in December 1979,
Jobs, then all of 24, had a privileged invitation to visit Xerox Parc.
And they showed me really three things.
But I was so blinded by the first one that
I didn't even really see the other two.
One of the things they showed me was object orienting programming
they showed me that but I didn't even see that.
The other one they showed me was a networked computer system...
they had over a hundred Alto computers all networked using email etc., etc.,
I didn't even see that.
I was so blinded by the first thing they showed me
which was the graphical user interface.
I thought it was the best thing I'd ever seen in my life.
Now remember it was very flawed, what we saw was incomplete,
they'd done a bunch of things wrong.
But we didn't know that at the time but still
though they had the germ of the idea was there and they'd done it very well
and within you know ten minutes it was obvious to me
that all computers would work like this some day.
It was a turning-point.
Jobs decided that this was the way forward for Apple.
He came back and I almost said asked, but the truth is,
demanded that his entire programming team
get a demo of the Smalltalk System
and the then head of the science centre
asked me to give the demo because Steve specifically asked
for me to give the demo and I said no way.
I had a big argument with these Xerox executives telling them
that they were about to give away the kitchen sink
and I said that I would only do it
if I were ordered to do it
cause then of course it would be their responsibility,
and that's what they did.
Demonstration:
The mouse is a pointing device that moves
a cursor around the display screen.
Adele and her colleagues showed the Apple programmers
an Alto machine running a graphical user interface.
Demonstration:
A selected window displays above other windows much like
place a piece of paper on top of a stack on a desk.
The visitors from Apple saw a computer
that was designed to be easy to use,
a machine that anybody could operate
and find friendly...even the French.
I think mostly what we got in that hour and a half
was inspiration and basically just sort of
a bolstering of our convictions that
a more graphical way to do things would make
this business computer more accessible.
After an hour looking at demos
they understood our technology, and what it meant
more than any Xerox executive understood
after years of showing it to them.
Basically they were copier heads that just had
no clue about a computer or what it could do.
And so they just grabbed eh grabbed defeat from
the greatest victory in the computer industry.
Xerox could have owned the entire computer industry today.
Could have been you know a company ten times its size.
Could have been IBM
could have been the IBM of the nineties.
Could have been the Microsoft of the nineties.
For Steve Jobs the road to Damascus passed through Palo Alto.
He persuaded the Apple board to invest in technology
copying what he'd seen at Xerox Parc - his instrument of change.
They hired a hundred engineers and started
developing a new PC codenamed Lisa.
But there were problems.
The Lisa didn't work properly and the
pricetag was heading toward $10,000
way too much for the average PC buyer.
Jobs' domineering style drove everyone nuts too
so the board ousted him from his own pet project.
You know I brooded for a few months,
but it was not very long after that
that it really occurred to me that
if we didn't do something here the
Apple 2 was running out of gas
and we needed to do something
with this technology fast or else
Apple might cease to exist as the company that it was.
Jobs got his answer from Jeff Raskin,
Apple employee number 31.
Raskin's idea was a $600 computer
as easy to use as a toaster
code-named Macintosh, after America's favourite apple.
Jobs liked the price but not Raskin's design ideas.
So Steve took over the Macintosh project,
determined to make it a cheaper Lisa.
And so I formed a small team to do the Macintosh
and we were on a mission from God
you know to save Apple.
While jobs persude his Mac mission,
he needed a more orthodox chief executive to run the company.
A respectable face, who could sell to corporate america.
He chose Pepsi-Cola executive, John sculley.
Sculley refused, Leave pepsi for a four year old company
that had been setup in a garage! Are you serious?!
But it was hard saying - No, to Steve jobs.
And then he looked up at me and just stared at me
with the stare that only Steve Jobs has
and he said do you want to sell sugar water for the rest of your life
or do you want to come with me and change the world
and I just gulped because I knew I would wonder
for the rest of my life what I would have missed.
For the young Mac team, average age 21,
this was the start of the toughest,
but most exhilarating assignment of their lives,
relentlessly driven by Jobs' ego.
BOB: Oh look at this and who is
this fresh-faced young guy here?
ANDY: That's me eleven years ago
had more hair I guess little thinner.
Oh I love these people.
They're like family to me really
and we were united by this common bond of trying
to do this incredible thing with the Mac.
Jobs wanted the Mac to revolutionise the PC market
so he insisted that the team deliver perfection.
Steve was upset that the Mac took too long to boot
to boot up when you first turned it on
so he tried motivating Larry Kenyon
by telling him well you know how many millions
of people are going to buy this machine
it's going to be millions of people
and let's imagine that
you can make it boot five seconds faster well that's
five seconds times a million every day that's fifty lifetimes,
if you can shave five seconds off
that you're saving fifty lives.
And so it was a nice way of thinking about it,
And we did get it to go faster.
And then this is one of the
very first Macintosh wire-wrap.
This is wire-wrap board No. 4.
As the Mac progressed, new features
were being continually added.
Jobs said the Mac had to be 'insanely great' and
pushed his engineers to the limit.
He had to - because by early 1983,
Apple was in trouble.
And this was what was giving Apple such a headache...
IBM's first PC launched in 1981.
It was a runaway success.
Within a couple of years more than
2 million units had been shipped
overtaking Apple and making Big Blue
the biggest player in the market.
Commercial:
When IBM personal computer owners look for good software
where can they turn - to IBM.
What was driving IBM PC sales was software...
Commercial:
Business programs, entertainment, productivity, education.
But software for an IBM wouldn't run on the Mac.
If the Macintosh was to succeed
Jobs needed killer applications.
Enter 25 year old software supremo Bill Gates.
At that time his company Microsoft
had one hundred workers
and was growing like crazy thanks to DOS,
the operating system that drove the IBM PC.
But DOS sure wasn't a GUI.
Gates and his aggressive number 2 Steve Ballmer
were immediately intrigued by the Mac.
Jobs talked to Bill at some industry conference
and said hey we're doing,
I think LISA was sort of in
development and he said
But i'm gonna do the graphical
interface machine here at Apple
Not just that LISA thing Bill I'm going to do the one
the one that's really going to be the winner.
While the Mac was being developed,
Jobs staged an event,
a parody of a TV game show,
to whip up enthusiasm among software developers.
And now ladies and gentlemen
the Macintosh Software Dating Game...
Jobs got the three top software bosses
of the time to sing the Mac's praises.
One of them was Bill Gates.
Steve didn't realise he was opening the door to the man
who'd prove to be Apple's main rival.
JOBS: When was your first date with the Macintosh?
GATES: We've been working with the Mac
for almost two years now
and we put some of our really good people on it and eh...
Even before we finished our work on the IBM PC,
Steve Jobs came and talked about what he wanted to do
that he thought he could do sort of a LISA but cheaper.
We said boy we'd love to help out.
The LISA had all its own applications
but of course they required a lot of memory ah
and we thought we could do better
and so Steve signed a deal with us to actually provide
bundled applications for the first Mac
and so we were big believers in the Mac
and what Steve was doing there.
Most people don't remember, but until the Mac,
Microsoft was not in the applications business...
it was dominated by Lotus.
And Microsoft took a big gamble to write for the Mac.
And so we got started in early 1982
on our Macintosh software effort and
I think at that point in time you know,
it really clicked with Bill that you know, graphic user interface
was going to be the way, the way of the future.
But while Bill was having his own GUI revelation,
Jobs believed that Apple's true enemy was IBM.
Will Big Blue dominate the entire computer industry...
the entire information age,
was George Orwell right about 1984?
Despite Steve Jobs' showmanship,
the IBM PC was hurting Apple's business.
And most pundits considered that...
Apple was going to be
out of business in a few short months.
Business Week ran an article on their cover saying
ehm "It's Over - IBM Has Won."
The Mac team saw themselves as Apple's pirates
but the gang was now being called on to save the ship,
as the Apple II was losing precious market share.
In the case of the Macintosh team,
they were behind schedule in getting the Mac out
which was not unusual in high technology
and so just getting that product to market
was extremely important.
After many delays, a date for
the launch of the Mac was announced.
The pressure of the deadline was mounting,
but Steve was still a perfectionist.
No design issue was too small and
it was never too late to do it right.
It was a pressure cooker.
We were working until we finished.
We couldn't go to sleep or anything
I was up for three days in that very last push
and finally the stars aligned and the last release
we made at six a.m. that morning.
It was now all or nothing,
because Lisa had turned out an expensive flop.
The fate of the whole company
seemed to rest on the launch of the Mac.
John Sculley had even authorised a
15 million dollar advertising campaign
to coincide with the Mac's public unveiling
January 24th, 1984.
I remember how nervous Steve was
before the introduction of the Macintosh
and the rehearsal the night before was a total disaster
nothing seemed to go right,
Steve was upset at everybody,
we wondered how in the world we were going to
get through the introduction the following day
but when that moment came
Steve was a master showman.
There have only been two milestone products in our industry
the Apple 2 in 1977 and the IBM PC in 1981.
Today...one year after LISA
we are introducing the third industry milestone product
...Macintosh.
Many of us have been working on
Macintosh for over two years now
and it has turned out insanely great.
You've just seen some pictures of Macintosh
now I'd like to show you Macintosh in person.
The Macintosh was undoubtedly the first affordable
personal computer with a genuine graphical user interface.
It was also the first computer to be
a monument to one man's ego.
Forget the brilliant work done at Xerox PARC
and the innovations borrowed from the Lisa.
On the day only one man was claiming paternity for the Mac.
Computer generated voice:
So it is with considerable pride, that I introduce a man
who's been like a father to me - Steve Jobs.
I was standing off-stage and as he came off
he said this is the proudest happiest moment
of my life and it was all over his face
it clearly was cause he had launched a revolution.
Ultimately it comes down to taste.
It comes down to trying to expose yourself to
the best things that humans have done
and then try to bring those things in to what you're doing.
I mean Picasso had a saying he said
good artists copy great artists steal.
And we have always been shameless
about stealing great ideas
and I think part of what made the Macintosh
great was that the people working on it
were musicians and poets and artists
and zoologists and historians
who also happened to be the best
computer scientists in the world.
With delusions of grandeur running rampant,
Apple created a Hollywood-style TV commercial.
It symbolised how the friendly Mac would free us
from the Orwellian tyranny of clunky IBM PC's.
Pleeeeeease!
Despite the hype, by late 1984,
the Mac's sales were disastrous.
In ad after ad, Apple desperately pointed out
that the Mac was far easier to use than the IBM PC.
But it sold for $2500
a thousand more than the IBM.
And despite Jobs' best efforts in recruiting
software makers like Bill Gates, applications were scarce.
It didn't do very much.
We had Mac Paint and Mac Write
were our only applications
and the market started to figure this out,
by the end of the year people said
well maybe the IBM PC isn't as easy to use
or is not as attractive as the Macintosh but
it actually does something that we want to be able to do
spreadsheets, wordprocessing and database
and so we started to see the sales of the Mac
tail off towards the end of 1984,
and that became a problem the following year.
Cringely's Third Law of Personal Computing was right again,
to succeed, a PC must have an application
which alone justifies buying the whole box.
The IBM PC had Lotus 1-2-3.
The Mac needed its killer application.
WYSIWYG - another bunch of initials,
from the world of the nerds.
What you see is what you get
so what's the big deal?
Well, it turns out that it's very hard to print on paper
exactly the same image that you see on the computer screen.
Eighty per cent of our brain is devoted to processing
visual data, but that's not the same for computers.
I've been here writing a letter to my Mum
and I'm signing it Bob in 72 point
Times Roman Italic type as befitting myself
and when I tell it to print,
what comes out is a Bob
but certainly not the Bob that I intended.
Until someone invented a way to print
exactly what was on the screen
gui would be, well a lot of hooey.
Apple's problem was the dot matrix printer.
It gave everything a type-writer quality.
But salvation was at hand and
once again it owed a lot to Xerox Parc.
One of Parc's former brains, John Warnock,
had invented a technology that allowed
a laser printer to print exactly,
precisely what was on your screen.
He started a company called Adobe
to market his invention
And what we had figured out how to do
that no-one else had figured out
how to do was drive laser printers.
Within two or three weeks
we had cancelled our internal project,
a bunch of people wanted to
kill me over this, but we did it
and I had cut a deal with Adobe user software
and we bought 19.9 per cent of Adobe at Apple.
The investment paid off.
The power of precise laser-printed images
and a user friendly gui gave birth to a brand new business
Desk-top publishing (DTP).
The spreadsheet had made us all accountants.
Now using break-through software
we could create fancy artwork,
snappy-looking note-paper, even counterfeit money.
The Mac had found its killer application
and would soon become the PC of choice
for any creative business.
It changed my life that one instant
when I picked up the mouse
my whole life changed to building
a career as a computer artist.
The success of desk-top publishing
came too late for Apple's founder.
In 1985 Mac sales were still flat
but Jobs refused to believe the numbers.
He simply behaved as if the Mac was
a hot seller from the start.
The grandiose plans of what
Macintosh were going to be
was just so far out of whack
with the truth of what the product was doing
and the truth of what the product was doing
was not horrible it was salvagable
but the gap between the two
was just so unthinkable
that somebody had to do something
and that somebody was John Sculley.
John Sculley, whom Jobs saw
as his own creation,
presented the board with
his strategy to save the company.
The plan did not include Steve Jobs.
The board had to make a choice,
and I said look, it's Steve's company,
I was brought in here to help you know,
if you want him to run it that's fine with me
but you know we've at least decide what
we're going to do and everyone has got to get behind it.
But he took it as a personal attack,
started attacking Scully in which you know,
backed himself into a corner because he was sure
that the board would support him and not Sculley.
And ehm ultimately after the board talked
with Steve and talked with me,
the decision was that we would go forward
with my plans and Steve left.
What can I say? I hired the wrong guy.
That was Sculley?
Yeah and eh he destroyed everything
I spent ten years working for.
Starting with me but that wasn't the saddest part.
I would have gladly left Apple if
Apple would have turned out like I wanted it to.
People in the company had
very mixed feelings about it.
Everyone had been terrorised by Steve Jobs
at some point or another and so there was a certain relief
that the terrorist will be gone
but on the other hand I think
there was an incredible respect
for Steve Jobs by the very same people
and we were all very worried
what would happen to this company
without the visionary, without the founder,
without the care, without the charisma...
Apple never recovered from losing Steve.
Steve was the heart and soul and driving force.
It would be quite a different place today.
They lost their soul.
The years after Jobs left were the most
profitable for Apple Computers.
Apple people worked hard, they played hard.
They made the computer business
look like a beach party
and with a median age of twenty seven
the company was very sexy too...
...maybe too sexy.
There was so much sleeping around that
they came up with a travel policy back then
that men would share rooms with other men on the road
and women with other women
just to settle it down a bit.
They applied the California lifestyle
to the computer industry
and the computer industry
would never be the same again.
In this bizarre promo to inspire their sales force,
Apple stressed that the Mac's ease of use could
liberate the pathetic prisoners of the IBM PC.
Commercial:
We'll fight them in the office and the classroom
and the desktop with superior weapons.
With improvements to the hardware
and the boom in desktop publishing,
Mac production went into overdrive.
By 1987, Apple was selling a million a year. IBM numbers!
The Mac minted money,
half its 2000 dollar price was pure profit!
Apple arrogantly assumed their stuff was so good,
consumers would always pay a premium for it.
Big mistake.
The Mac really ought to have
won the battle for the desktop
OK, it was more expensive than an IBM PC
but if what you wanted was a friendly
easy to use system and surely everyone wanted that,
then this was the only game in town
at least that's what the boys at Apple thought
but they weren't reckoning on one man, Bill Gates.
Gates saw that the Mac's GUI represented
a long term threat to Microsoft's money machine,
to DOS, the clunky operating system
that sat inside every IBM PC.
So Bill had his boys create a GUI
that sat in top of DOS
rather like building a fancy facade
on an old building.
They called it Windows and
it wasn't much at first
but it was good enough to
defend the DOS franchise.
February or March of 1984,
which was just right after the
Apple Macintosh had been introduced.
And at that point in time we were firmly convinced
that we needed to bet on graphic user interface.
First with the Macintosh
and then with Windows.
At Microsoft, it was a long and
often frustrating struggle
to find a GUI solution
that challenged the MAC.
I know the feeling!
For years teams of Microsofties slaved in
their windowless offices to build Windows
refreshed by an endless supply of free sodas.
I was the development manager for Windows 1.0
and we kept slogging and slogging
yeah it took us i don't know about seven versions
just a few versions to get
things right for 1990, that's right.
Windows may at first have been
a joke compared to the Mac.
But Gates is persistent. Slowly it got better.
And the guys at Apple got worried.
As each new feature appeared on the Windows gui,
the more they thought Microsoft
was copying the features on the Mac.
So finally they sued Microsoft,
accusing them in a long legal battle of
stealing the look and feel of Apple's GUI.
The look and feel which is how it looks,
the experience of using it was not patentable
but it was copyrightable
but there was no precedent law.
This was going to be a precedent setting case.
But it was a period of five years where, Microsoft
our whole strategy would have been ruined
because Windows was very important to us.
They weren't going to change anything and
they were going to get us to cave in
or take us all the way to
the Supreme Court on this thing.
We assumed that the lawyers, the judges would all
come to the right conclusion which eventually they did.
And Apple lost.
But in that period of about six years
that this case was going on
it may have lulled us into a
bit of complacency thinking that
we were going to be insulated,
you know, from the Windows attack.
The launch of Windows 3 in 1990
killed off Apple's hopes
that the Macintosh would win the gui wars.
Today we're introducing Microsoft Windows version 3...
The six years' labour to produce a GUI
that made IBM PCs and all the clones
as easy to use as the Mac finally came up trumps.
In a year Windows 3 sold close to 30 million copies,
consigning the Mac to a niche in the market.
Ladies and gentlemen the Windows 3 development team.
Bill Gates strategy won out.
At every stage in the PC's development
he joined the leading hardware company
and by carving out a dominant market share
for his product made his software the industry standard.
You know the original PC did our evangelism in the way
we created tools for that and pulled that together.
Take Windows did we bet our company on that
did that come together?
Virtually everything we've done,
when we've first come out with it there's a lot of scepticism
but most of the things we really stuck with them
and despite all that second guessing
we were able to pull them off.
The problem was the industry wasn't measured by
who has the best selling personal computer
or who has the most innovative technology.
The industry was measured by who had the most open system
that was adopted by the most other companies
and the Microsoft strategy ultimately turned out
to be the better business strategy.
The only problem with Microsoft is
they just have no taste,
they have absolutely no taste,
and what that means is
I don't mean that in a small way
I mean that in a big way.
In the sense that...
they, they don't think of original ideas and
they don't bring much culture into their product
and you say why is that important
well you know proportionally spaced fonts
come from type setting and beautiful books,
that's where one gets the idea
if it weren't for the Mac
they would never have that in their products
and so I guess I am saddened,
Not by Microsoft's success
I have no problem with their success,
they've earned their success for the most part.
I have a problem with the fact that
they just make really third rate products.
I will admit quite frankly that I think
Windows today is probably four years behind,
three years behind where it would have been
had we not danced with IBM for so long.
Because the amount of split energy,
split works, split IQ in the company
really cost our end customer
real innovation in our product line
and so whenever I hear these criticisms
which I gotta to say sting eh sometimes,
I say to myself just you watch,
just you watch Windows 95, Windows 9...
there's no lack of focus there hasn't been here
for the last three or four years
since we didn't have this big spot with IBM.
And i think even in the operating systems here now,
you'll start to see clear, clear...
and people will recognise clear leadership.
We just keep making them better.
We get millions of phone calls
we get to go out there and talk to customers
there's nothing cast in concrete. If people decide
there's something we should change we change it,
it's a lot better than most industries in that sense.
I think the way that applications user interfaces
have advanced over the last decade
Microsoft has been at the forefront
of a very high percentage of that,
and you know,
I think it's great stuff.
On August 24th 1995, Gates delivered
the coup de grace to his software rivals.
Windows 95 combines a PC's operating system
and its graphical interface into one package.
With a worldwide promotional campaign costing $300 million,
it looks set to become the industry standard
supplanting Microsoft's old warhorse DOS.
Cue the triumph of Bill.
A software nerd is the richest man in the world.
But even as Bill Gates bestrides
the PC world like a colossus,
ahead lie bigger battles, battles
that will make the trouncing of the Mac
and mastering the IBM PC
look like a tea party.
The Gates fortune was built on setting the
industry standard for PC operating systems.
Fine as long as PC's are
stand alone boxes on your desk.
But now they are being linked into a worldwide network,
the much hyped information superhighway.
The PC on the internet is a mailbox,
a telephone and a television.
Of course at the centre of this will be the idea of
digital convergence that is taking all the information
books, art, movies and being able to provide that
on demand on what the PC will have evolved into.
The Internet is the next wave of the information revolution
where there is as yet no industry standard,
a world where even Bill Gates seems unsure.
You know, if you take the way
the Internet is changing month by month,
if somebody can predict what's going to happen
three months from now, nine months from now
even today eh my hat's off to them,
I think we've got a phenomena here that is moving
so rapidly that nobody knows exactly where it will go.
Bill Gates isn't resting on his laurels.
He's making new alliances, like investing in
Steven Spielberg's new movie studio, Dreamworks.
He's in cable TV with broadcaster NBC and in
competition with Rupert Murdoch and Mickey Mouse.
These tycoons are a far cry from
the nerds Bill has so far outsmarted
guys like Gary Kildall who became
businessmen by accident.
Even Bill's victory over IBM was really with a corporate outpost
a long way from the attention of Big Blue Headquarters.
No - Bill's new rivals are hotshots, not hippies.
And one of them is the guy I'm visiting.
He hopes the Internet will go somewhere
other than to Bill Gates' bottom line.
He's betting it will soon consign the PC itself
to the trashcan and do the same to Microsoft.
Larry Ellison is the boss of Oracle,
a booming business that sells software to companies
who share information among hundreds of users.
In Atherton, the most exclusive suburb in Silicon Valley,
the bachelor billionaire has built himself
a 10 million dollar samurai mansion. Naturally!
I want to have a large pond about 5 acres of water
surrounded by several little buildings like a village.
With his ceremonial carp Larry contemplates
the coming battle with Microsoft.
People make a terrible mistake of thinking
IBM is the present and Microsoft is the future
I think IBM is the past and Microsoft is the present
and the future has not happened so we don't know what company,
what technology is going to be dominant.
These are temple guardians from the Koma Kura period
and, they you know you would have
one on either side of your door and,
the job was to scare employees of Microsoft away
and keep them from entering the Temple.
We shouldn't spend all of our time wringing our hands
about Microsoft you know
Microsoft world domination that eh
there still room enough for innovation.
there's going to be change and
Microsoft's future is not assured.
Anything good for the Internet.
Yeah I'm very supportive of it because
the Internet does not require a PC.
Larry believes the PC will be replaced with
a cheap device he calls an information appliance.
It will be a glorified television which will
access information and computing
simply by connecting to
giant computers via the Internet.
Just like turning on a tap.
and the PC will go the way of the well and the bucket.
I hate the PC with a passion.
Me going down to the store
and buying Windows 95,
I've got to get into my car drive down
to a store, buy a cardboard box full of bits,
you know encoded on a piece of plastic CDROM
and you bring it home and read a manual install this thing
you must be kidding you know,
put the stuff on the net
it's bits, don't put bits in cardboard,
cardboard in trucks, trucks to stores,
me go to the store, you know,
pick the stuff out, it's insane.
OK I love the Internet,
I want information you know it flows across the wire.
So, the way ahead is wired,
Larry, Bill, everybody agrees on that.
And we have the nerds of the seventies
to thank for making it possible,
whether the PC itself survives or not.
As we take up their challenge, it's worth finding out
how these pioneers made out.
Steve Jobs sold all his Apple stock
in disgust when he was fired,
but has made another fortune from
his stake in a movie animation studio.
He has no doubts about
his contribution to humanity.
If you talk to people that use
the Macintosh they love it
but you don't hear people loving products
very often you know really,
but you could feel it in there,
there was something really wonderful there.
Apple, the company Jobs took from a garage
to the Fortune 500 is in trouble.
It is now a fading force in the PC marketplace.
Apple's other millionaire founder Steve Wozniak,
spends much of his time teaching
computing to 11 and 12 year olds.
IBM created the mass market for the PC
but no longer sets industry standards.
And most of the guys who built
IBM's first PC have left Big Blue.
And Ed Roberts who built the Altair,
the very first PC,
he turned his back on computing
and returned to his first love, medicine.
Funny, isn't how things turn out?
After all the first PC revolution
caught us all pretty much by surprise.
Even Microsoft with 2000 millionaires
and at least two billionaires
never expected to be as successful
as they are today.
Cringely's universal law says,
Society takes 30 years to adopt new technology
into daily life, the phone, movies.
Even television took that long before
our rear ends became couch-shaped.
So far the PC has had 20 years.
So what comes next? Well, I'm off to find out.
See you in ten years!
Subtitles by [*** (V)r . |)  U    |2  E    ||  E ***]
from PBS transcripts,
(12/12/2007)
Inspired by,
fabiusX
from part I and II